Muriel Simonson Papers MS135
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Muriel Simonson Papers
1925 -- 1929
1908 -- 1981
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Simonson, Muriel
MS135
0.5 Linear Feet
48 Digital Object(s)
Arrangement
This collection is organized into one series.
Biographical / Historical
Born on April 25, 1907, Muriel Simonson graduated from Medford High School, Medford, MA, in 1924. The first woman in her family to go to college, Muriel was one of only two Medford freshmen at Jackson College in the fall of 1924. The Simonsons, a middle-class Medford family, lived on 23 and 26 Dudley Street, Medford, Massachusetts. Her father, Wilmot A. Simonson, was a traveling salesman selling fruit drink-mixes, biscuits, and Mrs. Simonson's Lemon Merengue Pies. Like many of her Jackson classmates, Muriel went on to excel in all areas while studying at Jackson College, Tufts' coordinate college for women established in 1910: academics, theater, voice, and theater production, as a sorority member, as a student leader, and as an athlete.
Unknown to Holmes scholars until 2006, Muriel Simonson and John A. Holmes (A1929) became officially engaged in the spring of 1929. John A. Holmes subsequently gave her a black, three-ring binder containing 24 poems written for and to Muriel. Sometime in 1930, the engagement was dissolved for currently unknown reasons, and Muriel went on to marry Jerry's father, Walter John Rhodes (1903-1996), a year later while John A. Holmes became a renowned local poet and professor of English at Tufts in 1934. Muriel, however, kept his poems tucked away at home and only her son's recent donation of her papers to the Digital Collections and Archvies brought them to light.
Like many women of her generation, Muriel stayed home after marriage -- despite her all her talents and her outstanding achievements while she was at Tufts. Her parents did not approve of her wish to become an actress given the profession's questionable reputation and the economic hardships of the late 1920s. Muriel Simonson Rhodes died November 14, 1987.
Custodial History
Material was donated by Jerry Rhodes, Muriel Simonson's son.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes family photographs, newspaper clippings from Tufts, theater programs, and a binder of poems by John Holmes given to Muriel Simonson circa 1930.
Alumni collections; University history; Tufts University -- History; Holmes, John A. (1904-62)
- Personal Papers, 1908 -- 1981; 1925 -- 1929; MS135.001; 0.5 Linear Feet; 48 Digital Object(s)
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes family photographs, newspaper clippings from Tufts, theater programs, and a John Holmes binder of poems given to Muriel Simonson ca 1930.
  Arrangement
  This series is not arranged.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Family Photographs, 1908 -- 1981; MS135.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
    - Muriel Simonson, age 1, 1908; MS135.001.001.00001.00001; Unknown (Box 1)
      Children; photographic print; Simonson, Muriel
    - Muriel Simonson with her mother at age 1, 1908; MS135.001.001.00001.00002; Unknown (Box 1)
      Family; Children; Women; photographic print; Simonson, Muriel
    - Muriel Simonson, age 5, with brother, 1912; MS135.001.001.00001.00003; Unknown (Box 1)
      Children; Family; photographic print; Simonson, Muriel
    - Muriel Simonson, age 17, 1924; MS135.001.001.00001.00004; Unknown (Box 1)
      People; photographic print; Simonson, Muriel
    - Muriel Simonson, 1922; MS135.001.001.00001.00005; Unknown (Box 1)
    - Muriel Simonson, 1945; MS135.001.001.00001.00006; Unknown (Box 1)
    - Muriel Simonson, 1955; MS135.001.001.00001.00007; Unknown (Box 1)
    - Muriel Simonson, 1981; MS135.001.001.00001.00008; Unknown (Box 1)
  - John Holmes Poetry, 1930; MS135.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
    Poetry given to Muriel Simonson by John Holmes.
    Holmes, John
    - John Holmes Poetry - 'V', 1930; MS135.001.001.00002.00001; Unknown
      Page 3 of poetry notebook given to Muriel Simonson by John A. Holmes, circa 1930. (First two are blank.) Poem begins 'There are faces,/People talk.'
      Poems; Holmes, John
    - John Holmes Poetry - 'XII' and 'XIII', 1930; MS135.001.001.00002.00002; Unknown
      Page 4 of poetry notebook given to Muriel Simonson by John A. Holmes, circa 1930. Poems begin 'Green candles and clean curtains' and 'I have lived richly friended'
    - John Holmes Poetry - 'XIV', 'XV' and 'XVI', 1930; MS135.001.001.00002.00003; Unknown
      Page 5 of poetry notebook given to Muriel Simonson by John A. Holmes, circa 1930. Poems begin 'It was all true, it was all true', 'Tall tree against the sky', and 'Did you sing to me'
    - John Holmes Poetry - 'XXII', 'XXIII' and 'XXIV', 1930; MS135.001.001.00002.00004; Unknown
      Page 6 of poetry notebook given to Muriel Simonson by John A. Holmes, circa 1930. Poems begin 'Even though tomorrow', 'When you have come at last', and 'Make me forget'
    - John Holmes Poetry - 'XXIX', 'XXX' and 'XXXI', 1930; MS135.001.001.00002.00005; Unknown
      Page 7 of poetry notebook given to Muriel Simonson by John A. Holmes, circa 1930. Poems begin 'You said, This newest height of love', 'I have lingered over making them', and 'You say the love I give you'. Following page is blank.
    - John Holmes Poetry - 'Poems For You, Jan. 4 - Feb. 1, 1930', 1930-01-04 -- 1930-02-01; MS135.001.001.00002.00006; Unknown
      Page 9 of poetry notebook given to Muriel Simonson by John A. Holmes, circa 1930. (Previous page is blank.)
    - John Holmes Poetry - 'In That Light', 1930; MS135.001.001.00002.00007; Unknown
      Page 10 of poetry notebook given to Muriel Simonson by John A. Holmes, circa 1930.
    - John Holmes Poetry - 'The Flowered Dress', 1930; MS135.001.001.00002.00008; Unknown
      Page 11 of poetry notebook given to Muriel Simonson by John A. Holmes, circa 1930. Poem continues on following page (Object MS135.001.001.00002.00009).
    - John Holmes Poetry - 'The Flowered Dress' (cont'd) and 'Shadow Upon Shadow', 1930; MS135.001.001.00002.00009; Unknown
      Page 12 of poetry notebook given to Muriel Simonson by John A. Holmes, circa 1930. Poem continued from previous page (Object MS135.001.001.00002.00008).
    - John Holmes Poetry - 'Fire-Music' and 'Reasons', 1930; MS135.001.001.00002.00010; Unknown
      Page 13 of poetry notebook given to Muriel Simonson by John A. Holmes, circa 1930.
    - John Holmes Poetry - 'Poems at Night', 1930; MS135.001.001.00002.00011; Unknown
      Page 14 of poetry notebook given to Muriel Simonson by John A. Holmes, circa 1930.
    - John Holmes Poetry - 'Always', 1930; MS135.001.001.00002.00012; Unknown
      Page 15 of poetry notebook given to Muriel Simonson by John A. Holmes, circa 1930.
    - John Holmes Poetry - 'To-Day is Gone' and 'Tomorrow', 1930; MS135.001.001.00002.00013; Unknown
      Page 16 of poetry notebook given to Muriel Simonson by John A. Holmes, circa 1930.
    - John Holmes Poetry - 'Beauty Beyond', 1930; MS135.001.001.00002.00014; Unknown
      Page 17 of poetry notebook given to Muriel Simonson by John A. Holmes, circa 1930.
    - John Holmes Poetry - 'Sonnet', 1930; MS135.001.001.00002.00015; Unknown
      Page 18 of poetry notebook given to Muriel Simonson by John A. Holmes, circa 1930.
    - John Holmes Poetry - 'Feb 18, 1930', MS135.001.001.00002.00016; Unknown
      Page 19 of poetry notebook given to Muriel Simonson by John A. Holmes, circa 1930.
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1925 -- 1931; MS135.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
    ca. 1925-1970s, bulk 1929-1930
    - 'A 1925 field hockey class', MS135.001.001.00003.00001.001; Unknown (Box 1)
      Newspaper clipping featuring photograph of field hockey team in uniform, with attached handwritten note. The printed photo caption indicates that this was the 1924 field hockey team, but a handwritten correction indicates that it is the 1925 field hockey team. The note, attached with cellophane tape, reads "This was in the latest issue of the 'Tufts Criterion' (a sort of newspaper) in connection with an article generally concerned with women's lib at Tufts for women. Egad, we thought we never had it so good, and felt completely 'libbed'!! First [indistinguishable] on left is Meg and the next I. Some outfits? My memory of field hockey is lots of fun -- plus"
      Field Hockey; Women; Athletics; hardcopies; Simonson, Muriel; Tufts University
    - 'A 1925 field hockey class' (reverse), MS135.001.001.00003.00001.002; Unknown (Box 1)
      Back of newspaper clipping featuring photograph of field hockey team in uniform, with attached handwritten note. Handwritten inscription on this side reads "the [indistinguishable] nonsense!" See MS135.001.001.00003.00001.001 for complete information.
    - 'Medford girl has leading feminine role in Othello', 1928; MS135.001.001.00003.00002; Unknown (Box 1)
      Clipping from unidentified Medford (Mass.) newspaper.
      Theater; hardcopies; Simonson, Muriel; Tufts University
    - 'Miss Simonson to Wed Editor Holmes of Tufts', 1929; MS135.001.001.00003.00003; Unknown (Box 1)
      Clipping from unidentified Medford (Mass.) newspaper. Includes photograph of Muriel Simonson. Subhead reads: Daughter of Mr. and Mrs. Wilmot H. Simonson of Dudley St. Engaged to John Albert Holmes, Jr. of West Somerville -- Both are Students at Jackson-Tufts and Receive Their Degrees This Month -- Both Are LEaders in College Activities on the Hill.
      Marriage; hardcopies; Simonson, Muriel; Holmes, John
    - 'In Tufts' Play', 1930-11-01; MS135.001.001.00003.00004; Unknown (Box 1)
      Clipping from Boston Post, Nov. 1, 1930. Photograph of Muriel Simonson, with caption: 'As a prominent feature of the celebration of Home-coming Day at Tufts College today, the college Dramatics Club will present Lonsdale's comedy 'The High Road' in Jackson Gym. Miss Muriel Simonson, '29, of Medford, will take a prominent part.'
    - 'Tufts Alumni To Return', 1931-10-31; MS135.001.001.00003.00005; Unknown (Box 1)
      Clipping from unidentified newspaper, Oct. 31, 1930. Photograph of Muriel Simonson, with caption: IN COMEDY ROLE: 'The High Road,' Frederick Lonsdale's comedy will have Miss Muriel Simonson of Medford in its cast when it is presented by the Tufts College Dramatics Club in the 'home-coming' day program tomorrow.
      Theater; Athletics; hardcopies; Simonson, Muriel; Tufts University
    - 'Rhodes-Simonson Nuptials Brilliant at First Baptist', 1931-10-12; MS135.001.001.00003.00006; Unknown (Box 1)
      Clipping from unidentified newspaper, Oct. 12, 1931, describing marriage of Muriel Simonson to Walter John Rhodes, Jr.
      Marriage; Church services; hardcopies; Simonson, Muriel; Rhodes, Walter John, Jr.; First Baptist Church, Medford
    - '17 Residents Here Take Part In Tufts Exercises' - Medford Mercury clipping featuring Muriel Simonson, 1929-06; MS135.001.001.00003.00007; Unknown (Box 1)
      Commencement; hardcopies; Simonson, Muriel; Tufts University
  - Photographs, 1925 -- 1938; MS135.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
    Photographs from Muriel Simonson's time at Tufts.
    - Freshman field hockey team, 1925; MS135.001.001.00004.00001.001; Munro, Melville S. (Box 1)
      Photograph of 1925 Tufts Freshman Field Hockey team. Photo by Prof. M. S. Munro. Back of photo identifies some of the players. (see MS135.001.001.00004.00001.002)
      Field Hockey; Athletics; Women; photographic print; Simonson, Muriel; Tufts University
    - Freshman field hockey team (reverse), 1925; MS135.001.001.00004.00001.002; Munro, Melville S. (Box 1)
      Back of photograph of 1925 Tufts Freshman Field Hockey team. Photo by Prof. M. S. Munro. (Front is MS135.001.001.00004.00001.001)
    - Sigma Kappa Sorority, 1926 -- 1927; MS135.001.001.00004.00002.001; Unknown (Box 1)
      Members of the Sigma Kappa Sorority at Tufts pose on the steps of a building on campus.
      Sororities; photographic print; Simonson, Muriel; Tufts University; Sigma Kappa
    - Sigma Kappa Sorority (reverse), 1926 -- 1927; MS135.001.001.00004.00002.002; Unknown (Box 1)
      Back of photo showing members of the Sigma Kappa Sorority at Tufts posing on the steps of a building on campus.
    - Tufts Varsity Field Hockey, 1927; MS135.001.001.00004.00003.001; Unknown (Box 1)
      Photograph showing 1927 Tufts University varsity field hockey team.
      Athletics; Field Hockey; Women; photographic print; Simonson, Muriel; Tufts University
    - Tufts Varsity Field Hockey (reverse), 1927; MS135.001.001.00004.00003.002; Unknown (Box 1)
      Back of photograph showing 1927 Tufts University varsity field hockey team.
    - Class of 1929, MS135.001.001.00004.00004.001; Unknown (Box 1)
      Photograph showing women from Tufts class of 1929 posing on the steps of a building draped with ivy and icicles.
      Women; photographic print; Simonson, Muriel; Tufts University
    - Class of 1929 (reverse), MS135.001.001.00004.00004.002; Unknown (Box 1)
      Back of photograph showing women from Tufts class of 1929 posing on the steps of a building draped with ivy and icicles.
    - 'The Show Off,' April, 1927; MS135.001.001.00004.00005.001; Unknown (Box 1)
      Photograph showing Muriel Simonson and Ben Tilden performing in 'The Show Off,' a play produced at Tufts in April, 1927.
      Theater; photographic print; Simonson, Muriel; Tufts University
    - 'The Show Off,' April (reverse), 1927; MS135.001.001.00004.00005.002; Unknown (Box 1)
      Back of photograph showing Muriel Simonson and Ben Tilden performing in 'The Show Off,' a play produced at Tufts in April, 1927.
    - Baby Party, 1928; MS135.001.001.00004.00006.001; Unknown (Box 1)
      Photograph showing Janet Pierce and Muriel Simonson performing in 'Baby Party,' a play produced at Tufts in 1928.
    - Baby Party (reverse), 1928; MS135.001.001.00004.00006.002; Unknown (Box 1)
      Back of photograph showing Janet Pierce and Muriel Simonson performing in 'Baby Party,' a play produced at Tufts in 1928.
    - Othello, April, 1928; MS135.001.001.00004.00007.001; Unknown (Box 1)
      Photograph showing Joe Nye, Alfredo Cary, Muriel Simonson, Doc Andrews, Ralph Hanso, Phil Bridges, Chet Gilson and Carol Coburn performing in 'Othello,' a play produced at Tufts in April, 1928.
    - Othello, April (reverse), 1928; MS135.001.001.00004.00007.002; Unknown (Box 1)
      Back of photograph showing Joe Nye, Alfredo Cary, Muriel Simonson, Doc Andrews, Ralph Hanso, Phil Bridges, Chet Gilson and Carol Coburn performing in 'Othello,' a play produced at Tufts in April, 1928.
    - Muriel Simonson and Doc Andrews in Othello, 1928; MS135.001.001.00004.00008.001; Unknown (Box 1)
      Photograph showing Muriel Simonson and Doc Andrews performing in 'Othello,' a play produced at Tufts in April, 1928.
    - Muriel Simonson and Doc Andrews in Othello (reverse), 1928; MS135.001.001.00004.00008.002; Unknown (Box 1)
      Back of photograph showing Muriel Simonson and Doc Andrews performing in 'Othello,' a play produced at Tufts in April, 1928.
    - 'Outward Bound', 1929; MS135.001.001.00004.00009.001; Unknown (Box 1)
      Photograph showing Bob Nicholson and Muriel Simonson performing in 'Outward Bound,' a play produced at Tufts in March, 1929.
    - 'Outward Bound' (reverse), 1929; MS135.001.001.00004.00009.002; Unknown (Box 1)
      Back of photograph showing Bob Nicholson and Muriel Simonson performing in 'Outward Bound,' a play produced at Tufts in March, 1929.
    - Scene from 'In Gilbert and Sullivan Land', 1929; MS135.001.001.00004.00010.001; Unknown (Box 1)
      Photograph showing Muriel Simonson, [Yaudier ?], Maurico Blodgett and Virginia Pettingill performing in 'In Gilbert and Sullivan Land,' a play produced at Tufts in February, 1929.
    - Scene from 'In Gilbert and Sullivan Land' (reverse), 1929; MS135.001.001.00004.00010.002; Unknown (Box 1)
      Back of photograph showing Muriel Simonson, [Yaudier ?], Maurico Blodgett and Virginia Pettingill performing in 'In Gilbert and Sullivan Land,' a play produced at Tufts in February, 1929.
    - 'In Gilbert and Sullivan Land' (Operetta) - Part of Josephine, 1929; MS135.001.001.00004.00011.001; Unknown (Box 1)
      Photograph showing Muriel Simonson wearing a kimono while playing the part of Josephine in 'In Gilbert and Sullivan Land,' a play produced at Tufts in February, 1929.
    - 'In Gilbert and Sullivan Land' (Operetta) - Part of Josephine (reverse), 1929; MS135.001.001.00004.00011.002; Unknown (Box 1)
      Back of photograph showing Muriel Simonson wearing a kimono while playing the part of Josephine in 'In Gilbert and Sullivan Land,' a play produced at Tufts in February, 1929.
    - 'The High Road', 1938-11-01; MS135.001.001.00004.00012.001; Unknown (Box 1)
      Photograph showing John Neal, Muriel Simonson, Ben Tilden, Art Tyrrel, Joe Nye, Wally Reddie,, Ray Fay, Mary Glidden and Doc Andrews performing in 'The High Road,' a play produced by Tufts alumni at Jackson Gym, Tufts College, November 1, 1930.
      Theater; Alumni and alumnae; photographic print; Simonson, Muriel; Tufts University
    - 'The High Road', 1938-11-01; MS135.001.001.00004.00012.002; Unknown (Box 1)
      Back of photograph showing John Neal, Muriel Simonson, Ben Tilden, Art Tyrrel, Joe Nye, Wally Reddie,, Ray Fay, Mary Glidden and Doc Andrews performing in 'The High Road,' a play produced by Tufts alumni at Jackson Gym, Tufts College, November 1, 1930.
  - Theater Programs, 1928 -- 1929; MS135.001.001.00005 (Box 1)